<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Avona, or, A transient view of the benefit of making rivers of this kingdom navigable occasioned by observing the scituation of the city of Salisbury upon the Avon, and the consequence of opening that river to that city : communicated by letter to a friend at London / by R.S.</title>
            <author>R. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12488673</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12488673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62326</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62326)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 290:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Avona, or, A transient view of the benefit of making rivers of this kingdom navigable occasioned by observing the scituation of the city of Salisbury upon the Avon, and the consequence of opening that river to that city : communicated by letter to a friend at London / by R.S.</title>
                  <author>R. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. &amp; N.T. for John Courtney ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rivers --  England.</term>
               <term>Avon, River (Leicestershire-Gloucestershire, England) --  Navigation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62326:1"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:62326:1"/>
               <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ON A;</hi> OR A TRANSIENT VIEW Of the Benefit of making RIVERS Of this Kingdom NAVIGABLE.</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED By obſerving the Scituation of the City of <hi>SALISBURY,</hi> upon the AVON, and the Conſequence of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that River to that City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communicated by Letter to a Friend at</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sola est fiducia Nilo.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> &amp; <hi>N. T.</hi> for <hi>John Courtney</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Sarum,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62326:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62326:2"/>
            <head>A Tranſient view of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of making the <hi>Avon</hi> by <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and other Rivers of this Kingdom Navigable.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Communicated by Letter to his Friend at</hi> London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O maintain that Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence (of ſo very great ſatisfaction and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage on my part) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun betwixt us, I ſhall give you an account of ſomething I met with in my way homewards from your great City, having nothing elſe ready at preſent; But
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62326:3"/>
by the next, I ſhall entertain you with ſome not inconſiderable obſervations made about theſe parts, and ſome very uſeful experiments, now almoſt perfected.</p>
            <p>I am ſure you remember, that the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Salisbury</hi> obtained an Act for making their River Navigable; but, as if that had been enough, they have hitherto ſpent all their firſt vigour in diſcourſe; But now, at my return, as if they meant to proceed effectually, they talk of nothing, but of procuring ſubſcriptions for raiſing Money; of agreeing with ſome able Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to undertake the work; And the Mayor and Commonalty of the City, have taken forth a Commiſſion under the Broad Seal, to impower them to go on with it: So that if they could not agree, 'tis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſome ſhort time may give beginning to the work; which, becauſe I have ſome affection for, I ſhall give you my thoughts of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Avon</hi> (you muſt know, having its Spring in the North-parts of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> holds on a courſe from North to South, of about Twenty Miles, by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p-Avon, Enford, Ames<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and by <hi>Stratford</hi> under the <hi>Old Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biodunum,</hi> to New <hi>Salisbury,</hi> upon its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62326:3"/>
to which City, divers ſmall Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels are derived from it; by which, part of it is conveyed through moſt of the Streets: The reſidue, in a large Bed, paſſes on the Weſt-ſide of the Town; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving run the whole length of the City and Cloſe, it receives at the South-Weſt Angle of the Cloſe, the <hi>Wily,</hi> and the <hi>Nadder:</hi> The former of which, riſing about <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and paſſing by <hi>Heytsbury,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving ſeveral Rills by the way, meets with the <hi>Nadder</hi> about <hi>Wilton;</hi> and from thence, they both paſs towards <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and joyn with the <hi>Avon</hi> at the place before named.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Avon</hi> increaſed by theſe two Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, (either of them near Twenty Miles diſtant from their firſt Springs, before this their laſt confluence) runs under <hi>Harnham Bridge,</hi> (which is that we paſs over in our way to the City from the Weſtern-parts) and within two or three Furlongs, receives another not inconſiderable River, from the North-Eaſt, at a place called <hi>Muttons Bridge;</hi> (betwixt which two Bridges, all thoſe ſeveral Rills which the City had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed out of the <hi>Avon,</hi> are returned again into its Channel) with the acceſs of which,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62326:4"/>
and ſeveral others in its courſe afterwards by <hi>Downton, Forthingbridge,</hi> and <hi>Ringwood</hi> in the New-Forreſt, it runs on to <hi>Christ-Church</hi> (about Twenty Mile from <hi>Saliſe)</hi> and there diſcharges it ſelf into the Sea.</p>
            <p>Whoever ſhall conſider the largeneſs of the River here at this place, and the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual increaſe of it in its paſſage to the Sea, will rather wonder, (as I have often done) that no benefit has been hitherto made of it, then any ways doubt, that it is able to anſwer the greateſt they can reaſonably expect from it: it reflecting very much upon the Inhabitants of this place, That when Nature had ſo opportunely provided a ſufficiency of Waters, They ſhould be ſo much wanting to themſelves, as not to afford thoſe Waters a convenient Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell.</p>
            <p>But, what you and I talked of the other day, of the ſeveral <hi>Genius</hi>'s of Ages, may have place here: And therefore, without being too ſevere to the diſcretion of this particular place, we ſhall be contented to charge this long overſight, upon the <hi>Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> of the foregoing Ages; which, its evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, was not ſo quick and active in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the means of improving what
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62326:4"/>
lay before them, as the preſent is: as is daily ſeen, not only in the great advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Art, and uſeful knowledge; in the improving of our Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in the ſame kind too: As appears by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Acts lately paſſed for making ſeveral of our Rivers Navigable; divers of which are ſince proſecuted to effect; A ſearching, thriving <hi>Genius;</hi> reſerv'd for this preſent Age to wait on, and perfect that Felicity which the paſt Calamities, it has ſafely emerg'd out of, will make it at laſt ſeem worthy of, and ſet off with a greater Luſtre: if our own ſupineſs, in not laying hold on thoſe opportunities it offers, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it not to eſcape us; ſince the particular <hi>Genius</hi> of every Age, (moving on upon the ſame Wheel that time does) being once paſs'd, is as irrevocable as that time that preſented it; both of them as they enter, ſo paſſing off together. And this is it may poſſibly awake the Inhabitants of this place, to endeavour to make a further uſe of the opportunity of their Scituation, and not to ſit down any longer contented with that little contrivance, which pleas'd their Anceſtors ſo very much, of cutting thoſe Channells I mention'd but now, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62326:5"/>
but this only uſe of the <hi>Avon,</hi> To keep their Streets clean. But to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to improve it to thoſe nobler advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, which the bounty of the River will moſt certainly afford e'm.</p>
            <p>For, to doubt of ſuch advantages to be made by making ſuch Rivers as this is, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigable, (as at my being here, ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen living thereabout in the Hill-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey (as they call it) did) is but a piece of ſtupidity as is not worth a refuting; it being all one, as to queſtion whether Navigation be advantagious or no? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as when things evident from ſenſe and experience are denied, we ſuperſede arguments, and bid our adverſaries only to make uſe of their ſenſes, and confute themſelves: So here, let any one who thinks otherwiſe, but only look about him, and obſerve the vaſt diſproportion between the wealth of ſuch places (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe equal) which are open to drive a Trade by Sea, and thoſe which are bound up within the Land, or, which is all one, the difference betwixt the Eſtate of a Tradeſman and of a Merchant.</p>
            <p>But there is more advantage to thoſe places, which being ſeated far within the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62326:5"/>
Land (as this is) do enjoy the benefit of Commerce by Sea, by ſome Navigable Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, then to thoſe Port-Towns which are ſeated in ſome Creeke or Bay only, and are (as I may call it) Land-lock'd, having no paſſage up into the Land but by Carriages; as we ſee in <hi>Poole</hi> and <hi>Lynn,</hi> in <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and in a number of other Port-Towns of like Scituation in other parts quite round the Iſland: For ſuch places, though the Sea brings in commodities to them, yet they can neither without great charge convey thoſe commodities higher up into the Land, nor, without the like charge, receive the Inn-land commodities to export again: Whereas, Cities ſeated upon Navigable Rivers far within the Land, look like ſome Noble Exchange of Natures own deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; where the Native and the Forreigner may immediately meet, and put off to each other the particular commodities of the growth of their own Countreys; the Native (as a Merchant) receiving the Forreign Goods at the firſt hand, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing his own for them at the very place where they are made, or grow; or at moſt, going no further to it, then to his ordinary Market.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62326:6"/>
And, as there is more of profit in ſuch a Scituation, ſo there is of Health and Pleaſantneſs; for we know, That Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, Quartanes, and other lingring Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, are more frequent near the Sea, then higher within the Land, where the Air coming to us from the Neighbouring Plains, Fields, and Woods, is more ſpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſtirring, and brings along with it the peculiar Health and Amenities of thoſe places it came from: Whereas, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants nigh the Sea muſt be content to take (as we uſe to ſay) one with t'other; And, as they enjoy the benefits which flow in upon e'm thence, ſo muſt they abide its inconveniencies too: But in ſuch Scituations as this, all the advantages of the Sea are fully and equally enjoyed with thoſe places ſeated nigh it, and only the injuries left out. And (if there be any thing in ſo ſlight a Remarque) the Scitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of thoſe places far within the Land upon ſome River, or in draught of the Sea, ſeems to carry more of State; when the Inhabitants, being remov'd at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (as in <hi>London, Antwerp,)</hi> and the wealth of the Sea waits on e'm at home, then when they go forth and attend it on the Shoar.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62326:6"/>
But it is not ſo much the pleaſure, or Healthineſs of a place that uſually takes the Common Inhabitant, much leſs its Scituation in point of Honour (as we may call it) as the profit and advantage he ſhall find in it. And this, as the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Salisbury</hi> in patticular may aſſure themſelves of, ſo may you and I, and the whole Kingdom, look upon this, and all other of like Nature, as upon works of a National and Publick Emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for when ſo many conſiderable places ſhall be enabled to look out toward a Trade at Sea, our ſtrength in Shipping and Mariners will be increaſed; Numbers of Lazy and Idle Perſons ſet on work; And that Royal Trade of Fiſhing, of ſo vaſt concernment to theſe Kingdoms, for which His Majeſty has laid ſuch excellent Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, will be very much advanc'd from the Number and Quality of Perſons in and nigh thoſe places. (and all almoſt ſuch Rivers in their courſe to the Sea) who, from the opportunity of their Scituation, will ſee themſelves ſo much concerned, for their own benefit, to purſue thoſe publick ends, which are inſeperably woven their private ones.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62326:7"/>
And here, give me leave to take a view, as they who having gained the top of ſome Mountain do, of a fair, but diſtant Landſchap towards which they are Travelling; whoſe extremities, though they appear faint, ſhady, and confus'd; And the particular objects ſeem broken; undiſtinguiſh'd, and blended together; yet the vaſtneſs of them is not the leſs conſiderable from that Indiſtinction, (it being rather an acceſs and reputation to Greatneſs, then any diminution to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it indeſinite) of the future Glory, which the effecting the preſent deſign of making our Rivers Navigable, will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly advance this Kingdom too: I would not have you think me too con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident in ſaying thus; for all the paſt and preſent experience of the whole World, will bear witneſs, of what infallible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence Navigation is to Opulence, Greatneſs, and Empire: And that, as thoſe People who Trade by Sea, ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways more abound in Wealth then the Inn-landers, ſo if a conteſt happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two ſuch People, the Maritime People ſhall always be of greater abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to maintain the Ware-And (the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62326:7"/>
of the People, and of their Chiefs, being otherwiſe equal) ſhall in fine prevail.</p>
            <p>Look back then upon the <hi>Phaenicians,</hi> elder than Storv, (for they flouriſh'd in the Fabulous Age) and you will find e'm great in themſelves, and greater in their Deſcendants and Colonies; power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful even to a Proverb; the extent of the <hi>Tyria Maria,</hi> being as vaſt, as the bounds of the then known Sea; To all which, the dread of their Power gave Law and Name: And that one City <hi>Tyre,</hi> ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole force of the <hi>Chaldaean</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy for thirteen years<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when in its oppugnation by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar. Every Head was made Bald, and every shoulder was Peel'd:</hi> (by carrying thoſe Materials which filling up the Seas that divided the Iſland on which <hi>Tyre</hi> ſtood, from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, enabled him to make his approaches by Land) abounding in all the plenty the Neighbouring Regions and Iſlands could afford e'm; in exchange for their fam'd <hi>Tyrian</hi> Purple: whilſt in the mean time, the Mountainers, and Hill-Country Gentlemen of <hi>Syria</hi> (like their Poſterity
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62326:8"/>
the preſent Wild <hi>Arabs)</hi> were forc'd to live upon the dry revenue of a barren deſert; their expeditions being chiefly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken againſt the next Neighbouring Flocks and Heards; and inſtead of cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing themſelves in Veſts of Silk, and Purple; acknowledg'd themſelves, in this only, obliged to the Indulgence of their Clime, which affording them Sun enough, might excuſe e'm from wearing any.</p>
            <p>Look next upon the Iſſue of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt betwixt thoſe two famous Cities, <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Sparta,</hi> in the <hi>Peloponneſian</hi> War; when, the <hi>Spartans,</hi> who lived upon the revenue of their Lands, thoſe Lands being waſted, were utterly diſabled any longer to maintain the War; nor could they, by all thoſe difficult habits of Sufferance and Frugality, buy up their Fortunes; But to the till then unknown diſhonour of the <hi>Spartan</hi> Name, which upon the ſtrength of a peculiar Diſcipline, had bore it ſelf up for four hundred years, were enforc'd to ſue for an unworthy Peace: Whereas the <hi>Athenians,</hi> their Territories being in like manner waſted by the <hi>Spartans,</hi> and their City block'd
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62326:8"/>
up towards the Land, liv'd, during that reſtraint, in all plenty; and recovering themſelves by their Trade at Sea, carryed over the War to the <hi>Spartans</hi> Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and prevailed over them in deſpight of virtue.</p>
            <p>The ſame is evident from the different abilities of the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians</hi> in the ſecond punick War; for, though the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> had bought the firſt Peace of the <hi>Romans</hi> for two Thouſand two Hundred Talents, to be paid in Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years; of which, a proportionable quantity was paid before the breaking out of the Second War; And though, in the ſame intervall, the <hi>Romans</hi> unjuſtly extorted other Twelve Hundred Talents (upon pretence, that ſome preparations which the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> made for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> were intended againſt <hi>Rome)</hi> and conſequently, at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Second War, the <hi>Romans</hi> were as much richer then the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> as the acceſs of thoſe Sums could make e'm; And the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> (beſides the loſs of thoſe Sums, being alſo in that interval, exhauſted by a dangerous War againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62326:9"/>
their Mercenaries) were ſo much poorer then otherwiſe they would have been; yet in that Second War, the ſpeedy growth of the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Wealth by their Sea-Trade, ſufficiently appears; When <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> carrying over the War into <hi>Italy,</hi> brought it before the Gates of <hi>Rome;</hi> and when, had the virtue of the <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginians</hi> been equal to that of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> or of their own General, affording him thoſe neceſſary ſupplies which were in their power to have yielded; <hi>Rome</hi> had been inevitably loſt; and the Senate wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon <hi>Hannibals</hi> Triumph: When con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe, the <hi>Romans,</hi> whoſe Revenue came from the Fruits of their Ground, were reduc'd by that War, to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream want, that they were not able to redeem their Priſoners taken at <hi>Cannae,</hi> though at that time they were in ſo great want of Men, that they were enforced to enroll their <hi>(Praetentati)</hi> Boyes in their Legions; and to borrow Eight Thouſand Slaves of their Maſters, to be paid for when the War was ended. This, <hi>Cato</hi> well obſerv'd in his uſual Cloſe, <hi>Deleatur Carthago!</hi> And the Senate fulfilled in their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62326:9"/>
Decree, to remove <hi>Carthage</hi> higher up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land; for, it was not <hi>Carthage</hi> that the <hi>Romans</hi> dreaded, but its Navigation; which had twice rais'd that City, greater out of its ruines; and would at length have given the Empire of the World to <hi>Carthage,</hi> and made <hi>Rome</hi> Tributary, had not its Twelve-miles removal from the Sea, founded an <hi>Inland-Carthage,</hi> which could no more be dreaded. And conform to this, you cannot but have obſerved, That the conſtant cuſtom of a prevailing power over its Emulous Adverſary, is, To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the number of its Veſſels.</p>
            <p>I need not name <hi>Venice</hi> to you; Their own Proverb will tell you what made e'm Rich <hi>(Il bianno &amp; il nero (cive Pope &amp; cottone) vanno futto Venetia ricca)</hi> White and Black <hi>(viit Pepper &amp; Cottin,</hi> thoſe inconſiderable ſmall Wares) have made <hi>Venice</hi> Rich: And you may then tell your ſelf what made e'm potent.</p>
            <p>The moſt admirable inſtance of this, are the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> by whoſe Navigation it came to paſs (ſays <hi>Grotius) ut Batavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inter arma foelicit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, non alicnam m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62326:10"/>
pacem, ſed &amp; ſuam vinceret.</hi> That the felicity of the <hi>Netherlanders</hi> in the midſt of War, did not only exceed that of the Peace of others, but of their own.</p>
            <p>But you will ask me, To what purpoſe is all this, ſince every body ſufficiently knows it? I confeſs, the truth is ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that I ought to ask Pardon for telling you over what all the World acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges; But you will certainly excuſe me, when you ſhall conſider, That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this confeſſed evidence, yet moſt Men know it to no purpoſe, refuſing to guide themſelves by that knowledge: Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a dull heavy temper, which reſtrains e'm within the ancient narrow Bounds which their Forefathers have caſt up about e'm; as if they knew and did all that was ever poſſible to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd; (which is the Common Errour of the Vulgar) and that to advance any further, and to paſs over thoſe Bounds, were a Treſpaſs, and a true Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Or out of a ridiculous Pride, (the errour of many of a better rank) which the wiſer of our own, and other Nations juſtly deride us for, accounting it beneath a Gentleman, to employ himſelf about any
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62326:10"/>
other thing, but the contriving how to paſs away his time the moſt vainly and unprofitably he can; running counter thus to all the wiſer parts of Mankind; who, truly ſenſible of the brevity of Life, and the long atchievments of Knowledge and Art, did from thoſe very reflections, quicken and excite their induſtry; and by a generous impatient ardour, made that very infelicity a ſtep to virtue; by huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding that ineſtimable, but waſting treaſure of time, to the utmoſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: Whereas we, on the contrary, not knowing how to employ our time, find it to be tedious to us; and complain of the length of thoſe hours, which all the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing World lament for their Brevity, and accuſe only of too much Wing: And therefore, finding our time to lie upon our hands, and to preſs us as a heavy Burthen, we ſtudy only how to ſpend it: And to this purpoſe, (and not for Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, after ſome more then ordinary in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of the Mind, but as our ſole buſineſs, worthy to take up all the Man, and the whole grand affair of Life, we purſue follies; and add to the already too ſpeedy courſe of our Hours, a more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62326:11"/>
flight by thoſe ſwifter vanities; which upon that account, we celebrate for the moſt excellent Paſtimes; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by them, attained the utmoſt End of all our endeavours and deep contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. To have yet further ſhortned and reduced our Span; and made our Age more nothing then it was, by paſſing its time away moſt inſenſibly and to no purpoſe: As if a worthy employment, either in any ingenuous (though Manual) labour by which Art might be advanc'd, which the greateſt Monarch of the Earth, the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> refuſes not; Or the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting ſuch publick works as theſe, for the good and honour of our Country; or the vouchſafing to deſcend to reap the beneſits accruing by them, by Traffick and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; which the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, diſdain not; but think the ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying their Veſſels, to be altogether as well as to Fight with them; (and by which means the <hi>Italian</hi> Gentry do (at leaſt) preſerve their ancient Patrimony) were not far more generous, then either to be Idle, or to become Slaves to our Vices, in doing the dull ſenſual Labours of Intemperance; and ſo commit the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62326:11"/>
charge of all other buſineſs to our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and reſerve to our ſelves only, the greater trouble of our own undoing.</p>
            <p>Whether it be any of theſe, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe it is that thus emaſculates and befools us, It will not be thought imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, by remembring the Bravery of the <hi>Tyrian,</hi> the ancient <hi>Spartan</hi> and <hi>Athenian</hi> Fate and Glory; <hi>Carthage</hi> even neere conquered, The fear of <hi>Rome;</hi> The no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Duration and Grandieur of <hi>Venice;</hi> And the Opulency of the <hi>Hoghan Moghans,</hi> to endeavour to awake us to the laying hold on thoſe Opportunities which are before us; <hi>viz.</hi> The eaſie work of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all our Rivers, capable of it, Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable; which when we ſhall have finiſh'd, and given our Iſland more Shoar then Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has afforded it, (the Sea, not only as now compaſſing, but entring us) That ſafety from without, which our moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Scituation already gives us, of being of difficult approach to its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and of eaſie deſcent for the Native, will be far more aſſur'd by the vaſt increaſe of our Shipping; which ſurrounding this our Iſland by their Wooden Walls, will afford it a protection greater then its
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62326:12"/>
own; A ſafety beyond what the Oracle promiſed <hi>Athens;</hi> and will be, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that Glorious Impreſs which incloſes His Majeſties Coynes, (and may it always His Septer!) <hi>Deus &amp; Tutamen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our ſafety from within too will be more aſſured: For People too numerous for the place that bred e'm, become, through want of employment, Poor, and conſequently diſcontented, reſtleſs, and unquiet; As Spirits in depauperated Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, grow iejune, and acid, exalting the terrene faculent parts: But as thoſe Spirits, by the affuſion of ſome more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Body, grow more benigne, ſedate, and temperate; ſo the Poor and Idle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put upon a full employment, their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly eager Spirits will convert all their powers on that; and be ſaded with the bounty of that employment; and the wealth that will wait on it: Which mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually advancing each other, the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firſt begetting wealth, and then that wealth a greater employment, ſhall eſtabliſh (what Art could never yet find out, nor Nature in particulars did ever yet perpetuate) a conſtantmotion, excited by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62326:12"/>
it ſelf, and by it ſelf continued and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd: Which inceſlantly moving on, and like a glorious Torrent, gathering New force and vigour from its progreſs, ſhall raiſe up a power and Felicity, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate, and boundleſs as the Cauſes which built it up; ſo far exceeding any of theirs we have before nam'd, as the diverſions of our Iſland, enlarg'd by thoſe vaſter Shores which our induſtry ſhall lay open, are, to the ſingle Haven of one City, <hi>Tyre or Carthage; Athens</hi> or <hi>Venice;</hi> Or to the narrow Shores of a Province or two: So that we ſhall no more need to reckon up the Examples of others, when we our ſelves ſhall be the Greateſt; nor to remember their Felicities, but to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend our own; and that Opulence, Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieur Empire which will undoubtedly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
            <p>And having thus gain'd to our ſelves Safety and Plenty; and a Power able to aſſure them to us, and be the warranty of thoſe Bleſſings, we may then have leiſure to attend thoſe further noble Superſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, which ſo firm and ſafe Foundations will aſſuredly ſuſtain.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62326:13"/>
Knowledge will be advanc'd; for when our ſelves ſhall have more fulfill'd that leading part of the Prophecy, <hi>Multi per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſibunt,</hi> That infallible Oracle which gave it forth, will compleat the following one, <hi>Augebitur Scientia.</hi> For when the whole Book of Nature ſhall be laid open, and the Story of her written over all the Face of the Earth, be made more legible, That Truth, which the World has in vain hitherto attempted, and ſought out of the dark Cells of Contemplative Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, (in which Pits ſhe has been hitherto buried) will then emerge, and manifeſt it ſelf, when the Conceptions we imagin, and frame in our ſelves, of thoſe umbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Schematiſmes, thoſe very ways, and viewleſs paths, which Nature ſignes and moves in, ſhall follow and be agreeable to the ſame real Truths of thoſe her ways in things, which our long, and moſt accurate Obſervation and Experience, ſhall firſt diſcover in thoſe things, ſcatter'd through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole extent of her Dominion; and not, when we ſhall firſt make Worlds of our own, and giving New Phanatick Laws to motion, ſhall endeavour to make Nature obedient to Scheme; and obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62326:13"/>
it with the greateſt earneſtneſs and Pride imaginable upon others, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit none elſe to e'm in quiet; but ſhall arrogate to our ſelves the ſole authority of being perpetnal Dictators both to Men and Nature. And then, thoſe Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom the inadverting part of the World vainly cenſures, for their ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully treaſuring up, the many little (as ſuch eſteem them) and mean Occurrences of Nature (as if there were any thing in the deſign or conduct of her Actions, mean; and but of ſmall regard; and that the moſt obvious; every-days wonders, did not diſcover a Wiſdom, high, and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to the utter diſhonour and confuſion of ours; and to the aſtoniſhment and higheſt veneration of all perſons, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the unwiſe Man who doth not well conſider it; and of the Fool, who will never underſtand it) ſhall receive the full, though late honour due to their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; when Poſterity, by diſpoſing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe ſcatter'd Leaves of Natures Oracles, gathered up by the diligent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers over all parts of the World, and depoſited with thoſe Candidates of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhall have eſtabliſht thoſe great and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62326:14"/>
general Truths, which all thoſe diſpers'd particulars ſhall conſent in, and bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to; And, as with fit materials, ſhall have erected that Auguſt Temple of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but ſlowly, and by degrees, as is the procedure of Nature in her own Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, when ſhe deſigns any thing firm, glorious, and permanent.</p>
            <p>And, as Knowledge, ſo will be Arts fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advanc'd; not only by importing thoſe of the product of other Countreys, (a Negotiation not ſo much heeded, as perhaps were fitting) but the active part among us, will be encouraged to confer new Donatives on the World; which they may as yet attempt with ſome unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: For, ſince thoſe (properly) Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Arts, which with greater Power, Speed, and Felicity, perform the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of many, by making uſe of other Aids then the immediate Hands of Men, may receive yet further advancement; but being advanc'd, ſince thoſe Multitudes of Hands, with which we already too much abound, will be then un-employed, whoſe helps are now requiſite; Thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Inventors, whoſe ſole End is the good
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62326:14"/>
of Mankind, imagine they ſhould<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fail of that great End, when by purchaſing to themſelves, the honour due to inventing and cultivating ſuch helps, they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the neceſſitous; whoſe neceſſary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence depending upon their immediate Labour, to excuſe their Labour, were to take away their Bread: Whereas, when our many Hands ſhall be otherwiſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, all helps will be acceptable; and the inventers of them receive their due Honours, not blaſted with the Curſes of the Indigent.</p>
            <p>I know you will be apt to ſmile at this, as a Fancy only; But let me ask you, how many Thouſand Pens are excus'd ſince the Art of Printing was invented, and our Libraries are no longer Manuſcripts? Which therefore muſt neceſſarily preſs in for a Livelyhood among other Arts, and overtook thoſe Profeſſions. How many poor Families would ſtarve, if the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sawing Mills were not (as out of Charity) ſuſpended? But to go no further for an inſtance then this very <hi>Salisbury;</hi> Some few years part, the mode
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62326:15"/>
of drawing Wyer, otherwiſe then by the Hand was brought into that City, by ſome from <hi>London;</hi> How did the poor Men of that Profeſſion (the Common Wyer-Drawers) ſuffer by that Intruſion? Who, as Men whoſe Countrey ſome po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Enemy had poſſeſs'd, being caſt out of their Employment, were enforc'd to ſeek out New Labours, or ſtarve upon their Old, not being able to work to their Maſters ſo cheap as the Engine could: Which proceſs, how obvious was it to have been found out ſooner? Or, for want of invention, how eaſily might it have been had from the famous <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſennus?</hi> who reported it as the practice of his Countrey many years ago?</p>
            <p>And the ſame will at all times fall out, when the unaſſiſted Arms of Men ſhall contend with the force of Engine; which latter therefore being preferr'd, ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the former; and the Invention, though worthy of all Honour, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily approv'd to uſe, ſhall become a Grievance; and engroſſing all Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into ſome Engines Dead Hand,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62326:15"/>
muſt awake the Laws in defence of the oppreſſed to wreſt it out thence, and arm it ſelf anew againſt that ſecond Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main.</p>
            <p>But (having firſt made way for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent uſe of ſuch Aids, and when to thoſe Aids, we ſhall add our own dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence (as ſome other Nations do) we ſhall not be obliged to envy the Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but managing our Labours with as few Hands as any, and as great a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſhall have no cauſe to complain that others can afford the proceeds of their Labours at a cheaper rate then we, and under-ſell ours, to the impairing and diſcouragement of Trade; but ſhall find, that ours will yield us as full returns as theirs, whenever we ſhall bring as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Aids as they, and an equal induſtry.</p>
            <p>What remains to be atchiev'd, (if what went before were not abundantly ſo too) will be Honour and Glory: For when Navigable Rivers ſhall be the Bounds of Villa's; and of thoſe the Ocean; and of it, the utmoſt extent of Nature; The
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62326:16"/>
opportunity of thoſe Scituations will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the more Generous among us to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade thoſe its furtheſt Borders; and in particular, that forlorn Company of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumeraries, who by a kind of Fatality are become a Proverb to the World, and rank'd among the other indigent Grandees of our Neighbour Nations (the <hi>Dons</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Minſieurs</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and the Barons of <hi>Germany,</hi> the younger Brothers of <hi>England,</hi> if they bring a virtue equal to their Poverty (and their Parents may do well to train e'm up eminently to the Firſt, ſince they endow them ſufficiently with the latter) will have a large Scheme open to exerciſe that virtue in; by diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, and planting thoſe many yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, and uncultivated Regions of the World; (for we are yet Strangers to thoſe vaſt Southern Tracts, nor do we know the amplitude of thoſe Continents whoſe Shores we inhabit) and by redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Salvage People to Humanity and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; not by thoſe ways the <hi>Spaniards</hi> heretofore took in the <hi>Indies,</hi> who by their incredible ravages, having rendred themſelves, and for their ſakes, Heaven
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62326:16"/>
it ſelf, abominated to the <hi>Indians,</hi> (for being courted to embrace our Religion, whoſe reward they were told, was the ſame Heaven that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded too; the Poor Wretches refuſed the Condition, and would not accept of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Company of the <hi>Spaniards)</hi> obſerved an ill Method to perſwade e'm to that Religion which was the Way to that End which they at firſt had taught them to abhor. Nor (as you remember we obſerved with Indignation out of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon's</hi> Hiſtory of the <hi>Barbado's)</hi> as our own Country-Men do there (and our Brethren in divers other places) who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to make any <hi>Negro</hi> a Chriſtian, leaſt they ſhould looſe the Slave; defacing at the ſame time that Chriſtianity in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which they refuſe to the <hi>Negro's;</hi> and converting all that loud zeal, and thoſe famous pretences of compaſſing Earth and Sea, for gaining Proſelytes to Heaven; to get poor Heathens to work their Plantations; and reſolving ſtill to keep e'm ſuch: Moſt unhappy Wretches! condemn'd to a firſt heavy thraldom here, and (as far as in us lies) to a ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62326:17"/>
one hereafter. From which, though their preſent Owners, (for whoſe ſakes only theſe poor Wretches ſeem to breath) believe, that they could preſent e'm with the only effectual means of their deliverance, yet, not to ſuſtain the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, by their Converſion, the hazard of the 30 pieces (the uſual price of a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>Negro,</hi> and the fatally preferred one to a rejected Saviour) they with-hold it from e'm; and refuſe to offer e'm a <hi>Redeemer</hi> from either Bondage; as altogether mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, inſtead of Religion, and the Goſpel, the Planting of Tobacco onely, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar-Canes.</p>
            <p>But, when theſe our more generous Colonies, ſhall have proſecuted Nobler Ends, more beſeeming Men and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; and propagated that Religion and Humanity abroad, which they ſhall have firſt Planted at home in their own Boſoms; They ſhall be no more a burthen to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Relations, but an Honour to both, and to their whole Nation: Their Names ſhall be Regiſtred among thoſe of the Nobleſt Order and Senſe of Mankind;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62326:17"/>
               <hi>Columbus, Americus, Magellane, Drake, Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh, Smith,</hi> &amp;c. And by ſubduing the minds of Men, more then their Bodies, ſhall be enobled with as great, but far more innocent Triumphs than <hi>Cortes</hi> and <hi>Pirarro</hi> for the Conqueſts of <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Mexico;</hi> In defect of Patrimony and Lands here; new Coaſts, and unknown Regions ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to e'm, and bear their Names: And, inſtead of owing all their Reputation to ſome Anceſtors expiring Merit, they ſhall gather freſh Honours from their proper virtue, and become the Sons of their own Fortune.</p>
            <p>As for that particular place, the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of which, firſt led me to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke: Whenever the preſent, or the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Inhabitants of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> by under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the advantage of their Scituation, ſhall have converted the <hi>Avon</hi> to more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſes, becoming ſo Noble a River, then thoſe very little ones it now ſerves for; They will then reap the true benefit of their deſcent from the Old dry Hill where their City was firſt ſeated; and ſhall celebrate their Names and Memories, who ſhall emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62326:18"/>
lead on, and advance the work, with their Churches Magnificent Founder, the famous <hi>Richard Poore;</hi> or their Canoniz'd <hi>Oſmund.</hi> The Adventurers and Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, beſides the Honour of being Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred for the promoting ſo noble a work, will find a fuller and more certain return for their Moneys, then had they purchaſed Land; or employed it at Intereſt; or any other known way amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The Merchants Company will not only be ſuch in Name, but will be truly ſuch, when they ſhall receive and export their Goods by Water at their own doors; and not, as now, make Voyages by Land to diſtant Haven Towns, and embark all their Merchandizes in Carts. The Magiſtrates will not need to put in practice any of their former petty ways of relief (as ſome call d e'm; but others, Grievances) as their New-Brew-houſe, and Leather-Tokens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor be enforc'd to burthen the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants with more Monethly Rates then there be Moneths in the year; when they ſhall be able to ſet all their Poor ſufficiently on work; the employment of the place,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62326:18"/>
being rather like to want Hands to manage it, than any Indigent Perſon want employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And generally, all conditions of Men, in, and nigh the place, will ſhare in the benefit the River will afford them; And the City which depends now for its ſubſiſtence, upon an Inn-land Trade, and the Weſtern Road, will acquire the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Port; and in the Catologue of the Cities of this Kingdom, be rank'd with <hi>Briſtoll.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62326:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62326:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
